Guide to the William Dwight Whitney Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Dwight Whitney family papers
1778-1951
1814-1912
MS 555
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.5
(57 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, journals and diaries, writings, legal and financial papers, and miscellanea of the William Dwight Whitney family, including William Dwight Whitney (1827-1894), his wife Elizabeth Wooster Baldwin Whitney (1824-1912), his brother Josiah Dwight Whitney (1819-1896), and his father Josiah Dwight Whitney (1786-1869). William Dwight Whitney material includes several hundred letters with his wife, journals and diaries (1843-1893), and a small quanity of professional papers. Material of his brother Josiah includes a geological survey of the Upper Mississippi (1862), and correspondence relating to the first systematic exploration and mapping of the American West. Information relating to Benjamin Silliman and the National Academy of Sciences is also documented. His family correspondence includes several hundred letters with William Dwight Whitney and their father, Josiah.
Whitney, William Dwight, 1827-1894
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the daughters of William Dwight Whitney, 1894-1959, and purchased from John Elliott, 1982.
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks of William Dwight Whitney are available on microfilm (128 frames on 1 reel, 35mm) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM107.
Biographical / Historical
Josiah Dwight Whitney was born on November 23, 1819 in Northampton, Massachusetts. He graduated from Yale College in 1839 (B.A.) and studied geology in Europe. He participated in the Lake Superior region survey (1847-1849) and several other expeditions through the 1860s. Whitney taught at Harvrd University and published several works on geology. He died in Lake Sunapee, New Hampshire on August 19, 1896.
Scope and Contents
The major part of this collection consists of the correspondence of William Dwight Whitney (1827-1894). There are also many letters of his brother Josiah Dwight Whitney (1819-1896). The academic careers of these two brothers were responsible, along with many other scholars represented in this collection, for the tremendous rise in the reputation of American scholarship which took place in the later nineteenth century.
William Dwight Whitney, Sanskritist and linguist began his teaching career at Yale in 1854 where he later organized and became the head of the modern language department of the Sheffield Scientific School. Among the numerous positions of honor which he held were the presidency of the American Oriental Society, foreign Knight of the Royal Prussian Order pour is mérite (succeeding Thomas Carlyle), and first president of the American Philological Association. (Extensive correspondence deals with all of the above.)
Nationally and internationally, Whitney gained prominence as Editor of the Century Dictionary, a position which made him the undisputed authority on the forth and usage of the English language in America. A prolonged and often heated dispute with Friedrich Max Müller of Oxford University over the origin and development of language earned for him the title of the champion of American scholarship here and in Europe. This verbal battle which is completely described in the collection was closely followed by the press with the result that Müller gained popular sympathy while Whitney was supported by many scientific scholars including Charles Darwin.
The personal letters of William Dwight Whitney are rich in New Haven and genealogical history. Mrs. Whitney was the daughter and sister of the Connecticut governors Roger Sherman Baldwin and Simeon Eben Baldwin and a cousin of Senator George Hoar and Edward Everett Hale. Whitney's sons, Edward Baldwin Whitney married Josepha Newcomb, the daughter of Simon Newcomb. Thus the Whitney family was linked with many of the most prominent families in America.
The correspondence of Josiah Dwight Whitney, although not as extensive as that of his brother, furnishes a great deal of information of the first systematic exploration and mapping of the American West. Most popularly known for his discovery of Mount Whitney while state geologist for the state of California, he published numerous scientific works and held an appointment to the faculty of Harvard University from 1865 until his death. Included in his letters is a revealing account of Benjamin Silliman's position in the controversial Emma Mine scandal.
This collection consists of 56 containers, holding approximately 35,000 items. The principal donors were the daughters of William Dwight Whitney. All items are catalogued individually.
Appendix
NOTED CORRESPONDENTS IN THE WILLIAM DWIGHT WHITNEY COLLECTION
Abbe, Cleveland 1838-1916
Abbot, Ezra 1819-1884
Adams, Henry Brooks 1838-1918
Adams, Henry Carter 1851-1921
Adams, John 1735-1826
Agassiz, Alexander 1835-1910
Agassiz, Louis 1807-1873
Aiken, Charles Augustus 1827-1892
Alger, William Rounseville 1822-1905
Allen, Frederic de Forest 1844-1897
Allen, William Francis 1830-1889
Ashmun, George 1804-1870
Aufrecht, Theodor 1822-1907
Avery, John 1837-1887
Bache, Alexander Dallas 1806-1867
Baird, Spencer Fullerton 1823-1887
Baldwin, Emily (Perkins) 1796-1874
Baldwin, George William 1832-1930
Baldwin, Henry 1832-1905
Baldwin, Henry de Forest 1862-1947
Baldwin, Roger Sherman 1869-1956
Baldwin, Simeon Eben 1840-1927
Ballou, William Hosea 1857-1937
Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter 1809-1889
Baynes, Thomas spencer 1823-1887
Beach, Frederick Converse 1848-1918
Beecher, Charles 1815-1900
Beecher, Charles: Emerson 1856-1904
Bickmore, Albert Smith 1839-1914
Bierstadt, Albert 1830-1902
Biot, Jean Baptiste 1774-1862
Bishop, Nathan 1808-1880
Bloomfield, Maurice 1855-1928
Boise, James Robinson 1815-1895
Booth, Newton 1825-1892
Botta, Anne Charlotte (Lynch) 1815-1891
Bowdoin, James 1726-1790
Bowles, Samuel 1826-1878
Bradley, Charles William 1807-1865
Bradley, Frank Howe 1838-1879
Brewer, William Henry 1828-1910
Brinton, Daniel Garrison 1837-1899
Bristed, Charles Astor 1820-1874
Brown, Francis 1849-1916
Brown, Samuel, Gilman 1813-1885
Browne, John Ross 1821-1875
Browne, William Hand 1828-1912
Brush, George Jarvis 1831-1912
Bumstead, Freeman Josiah 1826-1879
Bumstead, Horace 1841-1919
Burnett, Henry Lawrence 1838-1916
Camp, Mary
Campbell Henry Colin 1862-1923
Carter, Franklin 1837-1919
Caswell, Alexis 1799-1877
Cesnola, Luigi Palms di 1832-1904
Chadbourne, Paul Ansel 1823-1883
Chamberlain, Joseph 1836-1914
Chase, Pliny Earle 1820-1886
Child, Francis James 1825-1896
Clarke, Hyde 1815-1895
Clemens, Samuel Langhorne 1855-1910
Cogswell, Joseph Green 1786-1871
Conway Moncure Daniel 1832-1907
Cook, Albert Stanburrough 1853-1927
Cooke, Josiah Parsons 1827-1894
Cooke, "Theodore 1815-1871
Cornell, Ezra 1807-1874
Cowell, Edward Byles 1826-1903
Cust, Robert Needham 1821-1909
Cutter, Ephraim 1832-1917
Dana, Charles Anderson 1819-1897
Dana, James Dwight 1813-1895
Darwin, Charles Robert 1809-1882
Darwin, George Howard 1845-1912
Davis, John Chandler Bancroft 1822-1907
Dawes, Henry Laurens 1816-1903
Day, George Edward 1815-1905
Deane, Charles 1813-1889
Dennis, James Shepard 1842-1914
Dorsey, James Owen 1848-1895
Drisler, Henry 1818-1297
Dwight, Benjamin Woodbridge 1816-1889
Dwight, Timothy 1828-1916
Dwight, William
Davids, Thomas William Rhys 1843-1922
Delany, Martin Robinson 1812-1885
Eaton, Daniel Cady 1834-1895
Edwards, Amelia Blandford 1831-1892
Edwards, Bela Bates 1802-1852
Edwards, William Henry 1822-1909
Eliot, Charles William 1834-1926
Emerson, Ralph Waldo 1803-1882
Everett, Charles Carroll 1829-1900
Ewell, Benjamin Stoddert 1810-1894
Farnam Henry Walcott 1853-1933
Field, Cyrus West 1819-1892
Fields Henry Martyn 1822-1907
Fisher, George Park 1827-1909
Fisher Irving 1867-1947
Folwell, William Watts 1833-1929
Fosters Dwight 1828-1884
Foster, Henrietta Perkins (Baldwin) 1830-1910
Foster, Roger Sherman Baldwin 1857-1924
Gabb, William More 1839-1878
Garcin de Tassy, Joseph Heliodore Sagesse Vertu 1794-1878
Gibbs, George 1815-1873
Gibbs, Oliver Wolcott 1822-1908
Gildersleeve, Basil Lanneau 1831-1924
Gilman, Arthur 1837-1909
Gilman, Daniel Coit 1831-1908
Gilman, Nicholas Paine 1849-1912
Ginn, Edwin 1838-1914
Godkin, Edwin Lawrence 1831-1902
Goldstücker, Theodor 1821-1872
Goodwin, William Watson 1831-1912
Gorham, Nathaniel 1738-1796
Gould, Benjamin Apthorp 1824-1896
Gray, Asa 1810-1888
Green, William Henry 1825-1900
Greenough James Bradstreet 1833-1901
Grimm, Herman 1828-1901
Griswold, John Augustus 1818-1872
Griswold, William McCrillis 1853-1899
Gurney, Ephraim Whitman 1829-1886
Guyot, Arnold Henry 1807-1884
Habersham Joseph 1751-1815
Hadley, Arthur Twining 1856-1930
Hadley, James 1821-1872
Haight, Henry Huntly 1825-1878
Haldeman, Samuel Steman 1812-1880
Hale, Charles Reuben 1837-1900
Hale, Edward Everett 1822-1909
Hale Horatio 1817-1896
Hale, William Gardner 1849-1928
Hall, FitzEdward 1825-1901
Hall, Granville Stanley 1844-1924
Hall, Issas Hollister 1837-1896
Hall, James 1811-1898
Harkness, Albert 1822-1907
Harper, William Rainey 1856-1906
Harrington, Mark Walrod 1848-l926
Harris, Samuel 1814-1899
Harrison, James Albert 1848-1911
Hastings, Serranus Clinton 1814-1893
Hawley Joseph Roswell 1826-1905
Hayden Ferdinand Vandiveer 1829-1887
Henry, Joseph 1797-1878
Hewett, Waterman Thomas 1846-1921
Hibben, James 1824-1856
Higginson Thomas Wentworth 1823-1911
Hilgard, Julius Erasmus 1825-1891
Hitchcock Charles Henry
Hittell, John Shertzer 1825-1901
Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood 1827-1894
Hoar, Elizabeth 1814-1878
Hoar, George Frisbie 1826-1904
Hodge, Frederick Webb 1864-1956
Holden, Edward Singleton 1846-1914
Holt, Henry 1840-1926
Hooker, Worthington 1806-1867
Hopkins, Mark 1802-1887
Hopkins Samuel 1807-1887
Hoppin, James Mason 1820-1906
Howe, Julia Ward 1819-1910
Howells, William Dean 1837-1920
Hoyt, Albert Harrison 1826-1915
Hoyt, John Wesley 1831-1912
Hubbard, Gardiner Greene 1822-1897
Ingersoll, Charles Roberts 1821-1903
Jackson, Charles Thomas 1805-1880
Janes, Lewis George 1844-1901
Jenkins, Thornton Alexander 1811-1893
Johnson, William Woolsey 1841-1927
Jordan David Starr 1851-1931
Joy, Charles Arad 1823-1891
Joynes, Edward Southey 1834-l917
Kellogg, Martin 1828-1903
Kendrick, Asahel Clark 1809-1895
Key, Thomas Hewitt 1799-1875
King, Clarence 1842-1901
Kingsley, William L
Knapp, William Ireland 1835-1908
Kuhn, Adalbert 1812-1881
Lane, George Martin 1823-1897
Lanman, Charles Rockwell 1850-1941
Learned, Sarah Birdseye (Whitney) 1824-1864
LeConte, Joseph 1823-1901
Leidy, Joseph 1823-1891
Lepsius, Karl Richard 1810-1884
Lesley, [J] Peter 1819-1903
Lewis, Charlton Miner 1866-1903
Leypoldt, Frederick 1835-1884
Lockyer, Sir Joseph Norman 1836-1920
Lodge, Henry Cabot 1850-1924
Loomis, Elias 1811-1889
Lord, David Nevins 1792-1880
Lovering, Joseph 1813-1892
Lowell, James Russell 1819-1891
Lymank Benjamin Smith 1835-1920
McCartee, Divie Bethune 1820-1900
McCosh, James 1811-1894
Macdonell, Arthur Anthony 1854-1930
McGee, William John 1853-1912
Mckinstry, John Alexander 1811
Magill, Edward Hicks 1825-1907
Magoun, George Frederic 1821-1896
Manatt, James Irving 1845-1915
March, Francis Andrew 1825-1911
Marsh, Dwight Whitney 1823-1896
Marsh, Henry 1797-1852
Marsh, Othniel Charles 1831-1899
Martin, Willier Alexander Parsons 1827-1916
Mason, Otis Tufton 1838-1908
Mead, Charles Marsh 1836-1911
Meek, Fielding Bradford 1817-1876
Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin 1841-1924
Mitchell, Donald Grant 1822-1908
Moore, George Foot 1851-1931
Morgan, Lewis Henry 1818-1881
Mori, Arinori 1847-1889
Morse, Samuel Finley Breese 1791-1872
Morton, Henry 1836-1902
Muir, John 1810-1882
Müller, Frederick (Friedrick) Maximilian [Max] 1823-1900
Newberry, John Strong 1822-1892
Newcomb, Simon 1835-1909
Newton, Charles Thomas 1816-1894
Nichols, John Benjamin 1867-1954
Norton, Charles Eliot 1827-1908
Nott, Eliphalet 1773-1866
Oertel, Hans 1868-
Olcott, Henry Steel 1832-1907
Olmstead, Frederick Law 1822-1903
Owen, Sir Richard 1804-1892
Page, Walter Hines 1855-1918
Paine, John Alsop 1840-1912
Paul, Charles Kegan 1828-1902
Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer 1804-1894
Peckham, Stephen Farnam 1838-1918
Peirce, Benjamin 1809-1880
Peirce, James Mills 1834-1906
Perkins, Frances W. 1839-
Perkins, Frederic Beecher 1828-1899
Perrin, Bernadotte 1845-1920
Perry, Arthur Latham 1830-1905
Perry, Thomas Sergeant 1845-1928
Pertsch, Wilhelm 1832-1899
Peters, John Punnnett 1852-1921
Phelps, Austin 1820-1890
Phelps, William Walter 1839-1894
Pike, Albert, 1809-1891
Platt, Orville Hitchcock 1827-1905
Plimpton, George Arthur 1855-1936
Porter, John Addison 1822-1866
Porter, Noah 1811-1892
Porter, Samuel 1810-1901
Porter, Sarah 1813-1900
Powell, John Wesley 1834-1902
Putnam Elizabeth Noble (Whitney) 1822-1863
Putnam, Samuel Osgood
Quincy Josiah Phillips 1829-1910
Raymond, John Howard 1814-1878
Regnier, Jacques Auguste Adolphe 1804-1884
Reid, Whitelaw 1837-1912
Rhoads, James [E] 1828-1895
Rice, Charles 1841-1901
Richardson, Charles Francis 1851-1913
Ridpath, John Clark 1840-1900
Ripley, George 1802-1880
Rockhill William Woodville 1854-1914
Rogers, Harriet Burbank 1834-1919
Rogers, William Barton 1804-1882
Rost, Reinhold 1822-1896
Roth, Rudolph von 1821-1895
Salisbury, Edward Elbridge 1814-1901
Sanders, Frank Knight 1861-1933
Sargent, John Osborne 1811-1891
Scarborough, William Saunders 1852-1926
Schele de Vere, Maximillian 1820-1898
Schuyler, Eugene 1840-1890
Scribner, Charles 1821-1871
Sedgwick, William Thompson 1855-1921
Seelye, Laurenus Clark 1837-1924
Sewell, Amanda Brewster -1926
Seguin, Edward Constant 1843-1898
Seyfforth, Gustavus 1796-1885
Seymour, Thomas Day 1848-1907
Sheldon, Edward Stevens 1851-1925
Short, Charles 1821-1886
Silliman, Benjamin 1816-1885
Sloane, William Milligan 1850-1928
Smith, Benjamin Eli 1857-1913
Smith, Charles Sprague 1853-1910
Smith, John Lawrence 1818-1883
Smith, Roswell 1829-l892
Spiegel, Friedrich von 1820-1905
Spofford, Ainsworth Rand 1825-1908
Sprague, Homer Baxter 1829-1918
Stearns, William Augustus, [illegible] -1876
Stevenson, James 1840-1888
Strong, Caleb 1745-1819
Strong, Stephen Chester 1824-1909
Sumner, William. [illegible]raham 1840-1910
Tarbell, Frank Bigelow 1853-1920
Tarbox, Increase Miles 1815-1888
Taylor, Issaac 1829-1901
Taylor, Samuel Harvey 1807-1871
Tea11, Francis Augustus 1822-1894
Tenney, Edward Payson 1835-1916
Thacher, Thomas Anthony 1815-1886
Thayer, Alexander Wheelock 1817-1897
Thayer, James Bradley 1831-1902
Thayer, Joseph Henry 1828-1901
Thomas, Calvin 1854-1919
Thomas, Joseph 1811-1891
Thompson, Joseph Parrish 1819-1879
Thompson, Robert Ellis 1844-1924
Thompson, William Gilman 1856-1927
Ticknor, William Davis 1810-1864
Torrey, Charles Cutler 1863-
Toy, Crawford Howell 1836-1919
Trumbull, Henry Clary 1830-1903
Trumbull, James Hammond 1821-1897
Tutwiler, Henry 1807-1884
Tutwiler, Julia Strudwick 1841-1916
Tyler, Moses Coit 1835-1900
Tyndall, John 1820-1893
Van Am[illegible]inge John Howard 1835-1915
Van Name, Addison 1835-1922
Verrill, Addison Emery 1839-1926
Waldo, Horatio 1778-1846
Walker, Francis Amasa 1840-1897
Walker, Williston 1860-1922
Ward, William Hayes 1835-1916
Warren, Henry Clarke 1854-1899
Warren, william Fairfield 1833-1929
Waters, Lewis Edson 1837-1901
Waters, william Everett 1856-1924
Wayland, Francis 1826-1904
Weber, Albrecht Friedrich 1825-1901
Wedgewood, Hensleigh 1803-1891
Weir, John Ferguson 1841-1926
Wells, William Harvey 1812-1885
Wheeler, Benjamin Ide 1854-1927
Wheeler, William Adolphus 1833-1874
Wheelock, John 1754-1817
White, Andrew Dickinson 1832-1918
White, Richard Grant 1821-1885
Whitehouse, Frederick Cope 1842-1911
Whitney, Clarissa (James) 1801-1876
Whitney, Edward Baldwin 1857-1911
Whitney, Edward Payson 1833-c.1858
Whitney, Eli 1820-1895
Whitney, Elizabeth Wooster (Baldwin) 1824-1912
Whitney, Henry Mitchell 1843-1911
Whitney, James Lyman 1835-1910
Whitney, Josiah Dwight 1786-1869
Whitney, Josiah Dwight 1819-1896
Whitney, Louisa (Goddard) Howe 1819-1882
Whitney, Maria 1830-1910
Whitney, William Collins 1841-1904
Whitney, Marian Parker 1861-1946
Whitney' William Dwight 1827-1894
Whiten, James Morris 1833-1920
Williams, Talcott 1849-1928
Winchell, Alexander 1824-1891
Winlock, Joseph 1826-1875
Winslow, William Copley 1840-1925
Woodford, Arthur Burnham 1861-
Woolsey, Theodore Dwight 1801-1889
Wright, John Henry 1852-1908
Families; Geology -- United States; Literature -- History and criticism; Ornithology; Sanskrit language; Science; Mississippi River; New Haven (Conn.) -- History; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; West (U.S.); Educators; Geologists; Linguists; Philologists; Abbot, Ezra, 1819-1884; Adams, Henry, 1838-1918; Allen, F. D. (Frederic De Forest), 1844-1897; Avery, John, 1837-1887; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Baldwin, Emily Pitkin Perkins, 1796-1874; Baldwin, Simeon E. (Simeon Eben), 1840-1927; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Baynes, T. Spencer (Thomas Spencer), 1823-1887; Bloomfield, Maurice, 1855-1928; Bowles, Samuel, 1826-1878; Brewer, William Henry, 1828-1910; Bumstead, Freeman J. (Freeman Josiah), 1826-1879; Camp, Mary; Carter, Franklin, 1837-1919; Child, Francis James, 1825-1896; Cooke, Theodore, 1815-1871; Cowell, Edward B. (Edward Byles), 1826-1903; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Drisler, Henry, 1818-1897; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Dwight, William, 1831-1888; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926; Fisher, George Park, 1827-1909; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947; Foster, Henrietta Perkins Baldwin, 1830-1910; Gabb, William M.; Gilman, Daniel C. (Daniel Coit), 1831-1908; Ginn, Edwin, 1838-1914; Godkin, Edwin Lawrence, 1831-1902; Goodwin, William Watson, 1831-1912; Green, William Henry, 1825-1900; Gurney, Ephraim Whitman, 1829-1886; Hadley, James, 1821-1872; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Hall, Fitzedward, 1825-1901; Hall, Isaac H. (Isaac Hollister), 1837-1896; Hayden, F. V. (Ferdinand Vandeveer), 1829-1887; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Hibben, James, 1824-1856; Holt, Henry, 1840-1926; Hopkins, Mark, 1802-1887; Jackson, Charles T. (Charles Thomas), 1805-1880; Joy, Charles A. (Charles Arad), 1823-1891; Joynes, Edward S. (Edward Southey), 1834-1917; Kingsley, William Lathrop, 1824-1896; Kuhn, Adalbert, 1812-1881; Lane, George Martin, 1823-1897; Lanman, Charles Rockwell, 1850-1941; Learned, Sarah Birdseye Whitney, 1824-1864; Lepsius, Richard, 1810-1884; March, Francis Andrew, 1825-1911; Marsh, Dwight W. (Dwight Whitney), 1823-1896; Marsh, Othniel Charles, 1831-1899; Martin, W. A. P. (William Alexander Parsons), 1827-1916; McCartee, Divie Bethune, 1820-1900; McKinstry, John Alexander, 1811-; Muir, J. (John), 1810-1882; Müller, F. Max (Friedrich Max), 1823-1900; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908; Peckham, Stephen Farnum, 1839-1918; Perkins, Frances W., 1839-; Perry, Thomas Sergeant, 1845-1928; Pertsch, Wilhelm, 1832-1899; Putnam, Elizabeth Noble Whitney, 1822-1863; Putnam, Samuel Osgood; Regnier, Jacques Auguste Adolphe, 1804-1884; Ripley, George, 1802-1880; Rockhill, William Woodville, 1854-1914; Rost, Reinhold, 1822-1896; Roth, Rudolf von, 1821-1895; Salisbury, Edward Elbridge, 1814-1901; Schele de Vere, M. (Maximilian), 1820-1898; Scribner, Charles, 1821-1871; Short, Charles, 1821-1886; Smith, Roswell, 1829-1892; Strong, Stephen Chester, 1824-1909; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910; Thomas, Joseph, 1811-1891; Thompson, Joseph P. (Joseph Parrish), 1819-1879; Trumbull, J. Hammond (James Hammond), 1821-1897; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Van Name, Addison; Ward, William Hayes, 1835-1916; Weber, Albrecht, 1825-1901; Wheeler, William A. (William Adolphus), 1833-1874; Whitney, Clarissa James, 1801-1876; Whitney, Edward Baldwin, 1857-1911; Whitney, Edward Payson, 1833-ca. 1858; Whitney, Elizabeth Wooster Baldwin, 1824-1912; Whitney, Emily Henrietta; Whitney, Henry Mitchell, 1843-1911; Whitney, J. D. (Josiah Dwight), 1819-1896; Whitney, Josiah D. (Josiah Dwight), 1786-1869; Whitney, Margaret Dwight; Whitney, Maria, 1830-1910; Whitney, Marian P. (Marian Parker), 1861-; Whitney, Sarah Williston, 1800-1833; Whitney, William Dwight, 1827-1894; Whitney family; American Oriental Society; American Philological Association; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1778-(1814-1894)-1951; Series I
  - 1778 - 1843 August (Box 1)
  - 1843 September - 1846 (Box 2)
  - 1847 - 1850 April (Box 3)
  - 1850 May - 1853 (Box 4)
  - 1854 - 1855 October (Box 5)
  - 1855 November - 1857 (Box 6)
  - 1858 - 1860 July (Box 7)
  - 1860 August - 1862 June (Box 8)
  - 1862 July - 1864 February (Box 9)
  - 1864 March - 1865 July (Box 10)
  - 1865 August - 1866 August (Box 11)
  - 1866 September - 1867 August (Box 12)
  - 1867 September - 1868 August (Box 13)
  - 1868 September - 1869 August (Box 14)
  - 1869 September - 1870 July (Box 15)
  - 1870 August - 1871 June (Box 16)
  - 1871 July - 1872 February (Box 17)
  - 1872 March - 1872 November 21 (Box 18)
  - 1872 November 22 - 1873 July (Box 19)
  - 1873 August - 1874 February (Box 20)
  - 1874 March - October (Box 21)
  - 1874 November - 1875 May (Box 22)
  - 1875 June - 1876 January (Box 23)
  - 1876 February - September (Box 24)
  - 1876 October - 1877 April (Box 25)
  - 1877 May - December (Box 26)
  - 1878 January - October (Box 27)
  - 1878 November - 1879 September (Box 28)
  - 1879 October - 1880 August (Box 29)
  - 1880 September - 1881 June (Box 30)
  - 1881 July - 1882 March (Box 31)
  - 1882 April - December (Box 32)
  - 1883 January - October (Box 33)
  - 1883 November - 1884 August (Box 34)
  - 1884 September - 1885 May (Box 35)
  - 1885 June - 1886 March (Box 36)
  - 1886 April - 1887 April (Box 37)
  - 1887 May- 1888 July (Box 38)
  - 1888 August - 1889 June (Box 39)
  - 1889 July - 1890 July (Box 40)
  - 1890 August - 1891 October (Box 41)
  - 1891 November - 1892 December (Box 42)
  - 1893 January - November (Box 43)
  - 1893 December - 1895 May (Box 44)
  - 1895 June - 1951 (Box 45)
  - Undated of Elizabeth Whitney, A - Z (Box 45)
  - Undated of Elizabeth Whitney to Emily Perkins Baldwin (Box 45)
  - Undated
    - Maria Whitney to
      - W.D. Whitney (Box 46)
      - Other Whitneys (Box 46)
      - Elizabeth B. Whitney (Box 46)
    - Miscellaneous to Elizabeth B. Whitney (Box 46)
    - W.D. Whitney (Box 46)
    - Letters of various Whitneys (Box 46)
    - Miscellaneous, A - Z (Box 46)
    - Unidentified (Box 46)
- Papers of W. D. Whitney, (1839-1897)-1924; Series II
  - Journals and diaries
    - 1843 - 1855 (Box 47)
    - 1856 - 1887 (Box 48)
    - 1888 - 1893 (Box 49)
  - Writings
    - Lecture, "The Birds of the Connecticut River Valley," with posters announcing its delivery, 1849 March 1 (Box 49)
    - Eulogy for Clinton Camp, [1853?] (Box 49)
    - Critique of James Frederick McCurdy's AryoSemitic Speech removed from Whitney's copy of the book, [1881?] (Box 49)
    - Critique of Alexander Melville Bell's Visible Speech, undated (Box 49)
    - "Some forms of the Verb in the catapatha Brâhmana", undated (Box 49)
    - Bound manuscript, "Portion of the BhágwatGeetá", undated (Box 49)
  - Notebooks and notes
    - "Geometrical Diagrams", 1839-1840 (Box 49)
    - "Diagrams Drawn … Under the direction of H.B. Underhill", 1840 (Box 49)
    - "Book of Miscellanies," with lists of stuffed birds, eggs, and specimens of wood, 1842 June-1847 October (Box 49)
    - Ornithology, 1843 April 9 -May 24 (Box 49)
    - Translations of German literature, especially of works by Goethe and Tieck, 1843-1845 (Box 49)
    - Writings
      - Bound manuscript, "Atharva Veda Sanhita", Published as The Atharva-veda prâtiçákhya or Çâunakîyâ cataurâdhyâyikâ: text translation and notes by William D. Whitney… New Haven, The American Oriental Society, 1862., 1859 (Box 49A)
    - Ornithology, 1846-1849 (Box 50)
    - "Plants gathered and pressed during 1847", 1847 May-December (Box 50)